Preliminary Guide to the Kwame Alexander papers, 1990-2007 MS2244
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kwame Alexander papers
1990-2007
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Alexander, Kwame
MS2244
5 Linear Feet
This collection contains documents from Kwame Alexander and his two publishing companies - BlackWords Press and Alexander Publishing Group. The collection ranges in dates from 1990 until 2007.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Kwame Alexander, 2008 (Accession 2008.002)
Biographical Note
Kwame Alexander, a poet, publisher, playwright, producer, speaker, and performer, is the author of eight books -including the best-selling Do The Write Thing: 7 Steps to Publishing Success, Kupenda: Love Poems, Dancing Naked on the Floor: poems and essays, and The Way I Walk, a collection of young adult short stories. He has conducted standing-room only publishing workshops, delivered keynote speeches, and performed his cutting-edge brand of poetry to audiences at numerous conferences, colleges and venues throughout the world, including: Stratford-on-Avon, Brixton Town Hall, Oberlin College, UC Berkeley, Hampton University, Duke University, University of Maryland, America's Choice National Conference, Baltimore Writers Alliance, and the Gwendolyn Brooks Writers Conference. In the fall of 2006, Alexander served as keynote speaker, along with Naomi Shihab, at the New York State Council for Teachers of English Annual Conference. Alexander has produced over two-hundred literary related special events, including the First Annual Capital BookFest, a major literary arts festival sponsored by The Washington Post, Chick-fil-A, and The Literacy Council of Prince George's County. As a literary expert and commentator, he has appeared on a variety of television and radio programs including Fox News, Tavis Smiley, BET's Teen Summit, News Channel 8's Entertainment Forecast, NPR's Kojo Namdi Show, and several NBC and Fox affiliates. He has also been featured in the Washington Post, Poets and Writers Magazine, Publisher's Weekly, Detroit Metro-Times, Washington Times, Sacramento Observer, Baltimore Sun, Vibe Magazine, Source Magazine, and The Virginia Pilot-Ledger Star. The founder of two book publishing companies, BlackWords Press and the Alexander Publishing Group, Alexander is responsible for progressive and original fiction and non-fiction. He has published over forty authors in different genres, including: M. Dion Thompson, former Baltimore Sun reporter and author of the critically-acclaimed historical novel Walk Like A Natural Man; Lalita Noronha, author of the short story collection, Where Monsoons Cry; and Michael Datcher, Today Show Book Club Awardee and editor of Tough Love: The Life and Death of Tupac Shakur. He lives in Northern Virginia with his wife and daughter, where he hosts a weekly radio program, Word of Mouth, and serves as poet-in-the-schools for Crossland High School/Prince George's County Schools.
-- Biography compiled from Kwame Alexander's website, www.kwamealexander.com
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains documents from Kwame Alexander and his two publishing companies - BlackWords Press and Alexander Publishing Group. Though there is one CD in this collection, the bulk of the material is papers from Alexander's files. The collection ranges in dates from 1990 until 2007. The bulk of the work is from the first few years of the 21st Century.
His personal papers include drafts of plays, television shows, poems, and books that he has produced. They also include correspondence and documents from Alexander's stint as a teacher at the Nora School. The papers from Alexander's publishing companies include events produced by the companies and works they published. There are also extensive business records and correspondence.
The collection was donated by Kwame Alexander in 2008.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Creative output, Personal information, Publishing company documents.
Poetry; Plays (document genre); Washington (D.C.); Publications; Publicity; Television; Radio; Baltimore (Md.); Audiovisual material; Teachers; Alexander Publishing (Firm); Hughes, Langston; Black Words Press; Hurston/Wright Foundation
- Creative output, 2001-2007; MS2244 Series 1; 2 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is comprised of creative output by Kwame Alexander. These are primarily drafts, manuscripts, and editing notes. They range in date from 2001-1007. First, there are drafts and notes concerning Alexander's collection of poetry. These are drafts of a variety of poetry books Alexander has written. Next, there are drafts of Alexander's plays, in addition to papers concerning the production of these plays. Third, this series has various television and film scripts and ideas written by Alexander. These are followed by articles Alexander wrote for various periodicals. Finally, there are scripts and notes for Alexander's radio show.
  - Do the Write Thing - Early Draft, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Do the Write Thing - Draft, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Do the Write Thing - Final Proof, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Black Humor Calendar - Materials, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Crush - Edited Draft, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crush - Early Drafts, Comments, Reviews, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Crush - Digital Proof, 03/07/2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family Pictures - Score Sheets, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Family Pictures - Various Drafts, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family Pictures - Draft, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family Pictures - Draft, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family Pictures - Draft, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jazz, Jive & Jam - Drafts, notes, etc., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Seventh Son - Notes, clips, etc., 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Seventh Son - Draft script, rewrites, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Seventh Son - Draft, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jazz, Jive & Jam - Drafts, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jazz, Jive & Jam - Draft scripts, promo info, etc., 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nervosis - Draft, notes, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Nervosis, Notes, contracts, etc., 2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Staged Black/The Flow - press releases, info, etc., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Play publications, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Black Comedy, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Comes Love - Script, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Literally Speaking - notes, budgets, etc., 2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - HBCU Outreach Video - draft, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Small Business - Pilot script, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hip Hop Harry, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Celebrity Spades Challenge, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miss Black USA, 08/07/2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Nobody Owns the Sky - Scripts, correspondence, etc., 2006 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Keeping the Faith - draft script, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Misc. scripts, notes, audition files, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles written by Kwame Alexander (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Word of Mouth radio show - notes, ideas, scripts, etc., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Personal information, 1990-2007; MS2244 Series 2; 1 Linear foot
  This series is comprised of Alexander's personal papers. They do not specifically deal with his publishing companies, nor are they directly related to his creative output. These papers include correspondence, publicity, and other miscellaneous papers ranging in date from 1990-2007. They include general correspondence and his personal publicity. In addition, there are extensive papers concerning the two classes he taught for the Nora School, a private school in Silver Spring, MD. There are also papers relating to Alexander's term on the board of the Hurston/Wright Foundation.
  - Publishing information, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Publicity documents/Press kit, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Press clips, reviews, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Press clips, reviews, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Professional correspondence (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hurston/Wright Foundation board - correspondence, meetings, events, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Nora School - general information, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Nora School - Intro to TV Commercial Writing - assignments, tests, etc., 2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Nora School - Creative Writing - assignments, tests, etc., 2006 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Nora School - Creative Writing - assignments, tests, etc., 2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Black Issues Book Review, 05/2001-10/2002 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    General note
    Kwame Alexander served as the poetry editor for these two years.
- Publishing company information, 1990-2007; MS2244 Series 3; 2 Linear feet
  This series is comprised of papers concerning the work of Alexander's two publishing companies - BlackWords Press and Alexander Publishing Group. The collection is comprised of files on the media, contacts, and business correspondence. They range in date from 1990-2007. The papers deal with books written by other authors but edited and published by Alexander's companies. They also focus on the business and publicity matters of events sponsored by the two companies.
  - Various Kwame Alexander Productions - proofs, 1997-2003 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - BlackWords/APG - Scott Haskins, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - BlackWords/APG - Dion Thompson, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - BlackWords/APG - Media File, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - One Dead Preacher - Draft, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Tough Love - Final Edited Draft, 11/19/1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Tough Love - Promo materials, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Tough Love - Notes, promotional materials, press, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Tough Love - Promotional materials, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Antiquated Journals - other drafts, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Tough Love - Michael Datcher, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Tough Love - Proof, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - BlackWords/APG - business files, contracts, invoices, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - BlackWords/APG - Publicity, press, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 360: Poets Festival - Correspondence, 10/1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 360: Poets Festival - Business Documents, 10/1998 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - BlackWords proposal for MSBET, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Kwame Alexander events (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Events produced by Kwame Alexander (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Just Us - Final Layout Proof, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - BlackWords informational packet, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - BlackWords/APG - Notes, misc., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - BlackWords/APG - Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - BlackWords/APG - Contacts, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - BlackWords/APG - Labels, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Journal for writers: Do the Write Thing, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    This journal includes a few pages with handwritten notes.